So with the the native rewrite of this
originally fully JavaScript compiler,
what was the problem you were trying to
solve with the rewrite and why did you
end up write rewriting it in native
code?
>> Well, I mean the the problem we were
trying to solve it's real simple
performance and scalability.
>> JavaScript was never really optimized
for compute inensive workloads like
compilers, right? JavaScript is more
about creating UI that runs in a
browser. Was originally intended for
just like maybe a 100 lines of code, but
now of course it's gotten to be a lot
more. Um, but it's not it's not a place
that that you would optimize for um for
the kind of workload that that we are.
So in JavaScript, first of all, you pay
a 2 to 3x perf penalty compared to
native code. I mean it depends on on the
workload you know but that's but if if
you're doing compute that's about where
it's at. Um and then secondly in
JavaScript there are a lot of
restrictions around use of concurrency.
Uh JavaScript was always engineered in
fact to be a single threaded language.
That's why we have callbacks and async
and and and whatever. It's because you
can't spin up threads. Um, and that's a
good thing mostly because concurrency in
a language with mutable data is very
very hard because you can have races and
deadlocks and all of this good stuff,
right? That's why functional programming
languages are easier with concurrency
because all the data is immutable and
it's much easier to reason about. Um
so JavaScript doesn't give you access to
concurrency other than web workers and
but web workers can't share data between
each other other than by remoting it. So
you can you can have one web worker
compute some something but if it wants
to give it to some other web worker it
has to turn it into JSON or it can't
just hand it objects and that means you
can't have one worker compute some data
structure and then have someone else use
it. In other words, you can't have
shared memory concurrency. And really
that's what we wanted in order to gain
all of the perf that we were leaving on
the table by not utilizing multi-core
CPUs that everyone has today, right?
Because Moore's law has stopped giving
us faster CPUs. It's giving us more CPUs
and we got to like find ways to use them
in our in our compute intensive
workloads or else we're leaving money on
the table. And so we were leaving money
on the table in multiple ways, right?
And so native code and that was why we
we looked for a language that
would get us out of both of those binds.
It had to be native and it had to have
access to shared memory concurrency.
>> I saw for the language choice you went
with Go. And when I think of all the
systems languages, the ones that are
often hot or maybe you know Rust or
Zigg, why did you choose Go for the
native rewrite? I think the decision
process was actually pretty structured.
You know, the first decision we made was
we're not going to rewrite. We're going
to port because only by porting can we
preserve the semantics and the
algorithms and the exact behavior of our
existing compiler which everyone depends
on for backwards compatibility. Now we
could have we could have cleaned the
slate and started completely from
scratch but we would have come we would
have come up with a different language
in the sense that it would give you
different errors or behave differently
in certain situations where it has to
make choices between multiple
possibilities and and what have you.
Right? So we wanted to port and that
meant our code makes certain assumptions
like our code for example assumes the
existence of garbage collection. It
assumes the existence of first class um
uh treatment of functions. You know, you
can have functions within functions and
you can close over over out of state and
so forth. Um and as we evaluated all of
these,
go was was the one that checked the most
boxes. You know, it gives us it gives us
very robust and mature native code
generation on all major platforms. It
has garbage collection and it has access
excellent access to shared memory
concurrency. Um, and those were like the
high order bits that we wanted to check.
And every other language had something
that kind of worked against those
objectives. So for this particular
workload, Go was the right was the right
choice for us and it's worked out well.
>> If you think about Rusk, what didn't it
have that if it had it, you would have
picked it? I mean I think there are
there are there are two things um it
doesn't have uh garbage collection
it's done manually you know uh well or
it's done through the borrow checker but
the borrow checker doesn't allow
circular data structures and our
compiler is chalk full of circular data
structures we have trees with parent
pointers we have types that are
recursive we have symbols that refer I
mean it's everywhere and like I said if
we had chosen to rewrite we could
probably solved all of that, but it
wouldn't have been just porting the
code. It would also have been like
solving a whole bunch of new problems
that we had bought ourselves by by going
that route. We tried [laughter]
and it just wasn't feasible, you know,
uh and and and so so we were we were
just trying to optimize for, you know,
doing as little work as possible to get
us to the payout, which is which and
honestly, Rust is no better when it
comes to like the quality of the
generated code or the or the the
concurrency gains that we could have
gotten out of it.
Go just it's great. I mean, so so we got
we got all the bennies with for less
work by by going that route.
>> I know some languages they're when you
say they're garbage collected, they
>> there's something in the the language
itself that is doing garbage collection,
but um there's also independent
libraries that can provide garbage
collection, right?
There is, but it it but it comes often
with a whole bunch of restrictions and
and and it doesn't come necessarily with
the safety guarantees that we were
looking for. I mean like Go is type safe
and memory safe. uh meaning that you
don't get to just like have stray
pointers or or whatever where rust you
can do ref counting or you can do you
can do all sorts of different strategies
but there's always like that little bit
of unsafe where you have to like do this
in order to make it all work you know uh
where where if garbage collection is
engineered into the language it really
is a a separate concern that is you you
you don't you don't have to do anything
special in I mean of course you you you
have to like not hold on to data that
you no longer need and whatever you know
but that's true of ref counting as well
right but but it is inherent in in the
language